Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"ח, Samech Chet,
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 68, and we pick up on ס"ז עמוד
ב', Samech Zayin Amud Bet, פשיטא, peshita, about 15 lines from the
bottom, last word on the line after the two dots. And our
learning should be for the for the זכות zechus of the חיילים
וחיילות chayalim v'chayalot and a speedy end of the war and a
speedy end of all of the unrest on the campuses. All right,
so we're in the middle of dealing with the whole issue of
a משכנתא mashkanta and
being in possession of somebody's field or or land or home while
there's a loan out against the person and whether that's a problem
of ריבית ribbis or not. So we will pick up here with
the two dots. פשיטא, peshita, it's obvious באתרא דמסלקי basra d'mesalki in
a place where the practice is is that the person who lent
the money is inhabiting the home or the field, let's say the
field, that's רש"י Rashi emphasizes that it's a case of a field
because you're not certain that you'll get a profit. So he is
on the property, the field of the person who borrowed the money
and he is
planting and harvesting and reaping and so on. And how it's not
going against the the what do you call it the principal? Presumably
it is not a משכנתא דסורא. mashkanta d'sura. And why is it
not ריבית? ribbis? Well, it's not ריבית דאורייתא ribbis d'oraisa
because
there is it's possible that there won't be any definite definite profit.
You have to like plant and harvest and and so and there
won't necessarily be profit. And according to some of the opinions in
the גמרא gemara earlier, if it was בנכייתא, b'nachyata,
if it was with deducting a certain fixed amount even if it
was a relatively small amount, that might make it even totally permissible,
although there was debate about that whether נכייתא nachyata would make it
permissible to תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, to everybody and so on. Okay,
but in one of the scenarios in which it's allowed, this person
is here on the land and it's a place דמסלקי. d'mesalki. It's
a place where the borrower has the right when he to pay
up the the loan at any time and to get the lender
off of his property. All right, and we saw that there were
two types of ways in which it could be done: באתרא דמסלקי
basra d'mesalki and an באתרא דלא מסלקי basra d'lo mesalki where the
borrower did not have the right to pay up the loan and
get the person off the property within a certain period of time.
The person who lent the money has absolute rights to that property
for a duration: a year, two years, five years. And interestingly, that
actually is less of a ריבית ribbis problem because it's more like
a sale and since that person has absolute rights during that period
of time it's like he's purchased that land and therefore there's less
of a problem of him reaping the benefits of the land. Okay,
but this is in a place of מסלקי mesalki where the borrower
does have the right to remove the lender if he pays up
the
debt. Okay, באתרא דמסלקי ואמר לא מסתלקנא basra d'mesalki v'amar lo mistalkina
and the person when he is lending the money says,
I'm only doing this under the understanding that you do not have
the right to remove me from the land. So הכא דלא מסתלקנא,
haca d'lo mistalkina, but he's saying that's the condition he's making when
he's lending the money only on the right that you cannot remove
me from the land. So that condition is obviously binding. So that
goes without saying that he makes that condition and it's automatically binding.
אלא באתרא דלא מסלקי ואמר מסתלקנא, ella basra d'lo mesalki v'amar mistalkina,
but how about if it's the reverse? It's a place where normally
you cannot remove the owner from the the lender from the land.
But he says, you know what, I'm going to do you a
favor and I will allow you to remove me from the land
whenever you pay up the debt. מאי, mai, what's the story? You
know obviously you can make conditions, but do the words themselves affect,
you know, are they sufficient? צריך למקני מיניה או לא? tzarich lemikni
minei o lo? Do you have to do a קניין kinyan or
not in order to make that binding?
רב פפא אמר לא צריך למקני מיניה, Rav Pappa amar lo tzarich
lemikni minei, you do not have to, once he's agreeing to allow
himself to be removed that becomes binding. רב ששת בריה
דרב אידי אמר צריך למקני מיניה, Rav Sheshes brei d'Rav Idi amar
tzarich lemikni minei, no you have to do a קניין, kinyan, you
have to like do a handkerchief or whatever to make it a
binding agreement. והלכתא, vehilchasa, the הלכה halakha is צריך למקני מיניה, tzarich
lemikni minei, you have to actually do a קניין kinyan to make
that binding. Now why should it matter which direction you do? So
you could say well, if he's lending the money and saying I'm
only lending the money on the condition that you know, I have
rights to the that you cannot get me off, okay, that's the
condition he's making for lending the money. But if he's lending the
money and saying I'll agree to go off, then you know, maybe
he's just you know, offering it, he's not being
serious, he's being nice, so maybe you know that should not be
seen as binding. Now of course what the ראשונים rishonim ask is...
Okay, but there's two people in this exchange. The borrower, when the
lender says, I'm lending you this money and you'll have the right
to kick me off, and the borrower says yes, on that condition
that I'm borrowing the money, so we should say, the borrower only
agreed to take the money and to borrow it on the condition
that he could kick the person off. So why don't we say
the same way the lender can make a stipulation, even if the
lender is the one that voices the stipulation of going easy, it's
implicit that the borrower is equally stipulating that only under those conditions
is he agreeing to the exchange. So it's not clear really why
it matters who is saying it, since in the end it's an
exchange and each side has to agree to it. So, you know,
תוספות Tosafot says, well, we're talking after the money was lent, but
then it's really not about what's being stipulated, it's really was it
being said at the time of the lending of the money or
after the money is being lent. So the רמב"ן Ramban says that
it's more about who's on the land. If the lender is on
the land and he says, you know, I'm not going to be
removed and the borrower is silent, then the lender is taking possession
of that land. He's there and his that's itself the קניין. kinyan.
But if he says I will allow you to remove me, this
is after the money has switched hands, then what is the borrower
doing that gives him rights back to the land? So that's the
way the רמב"ן Ramban focuses on it, that it's after the money
has been lent and the point
is
since the lender is in possession, he can take more rights by
staying on the land if the borrower agrees, but if the borrower
wants to get more rights in the exchange after the money has
been lent and he is not on the land, they have to
do a קניין. kinyan. Okay. That's that. Now, אמר
איזהו נכייתא.
Amar eizehu
nechyata.
So let's say in a place where you're מסלקי, mesalki, right, you
can kick the guy off, he says the lender says, wait, I
got—I have the money, I'm going to the ATM machine and I
don't want you to be taking any more of the harvesting or
whatever because I am right now ready to pay up. So then
לא אכיל, lo achil, then the lender does not have a right
to eat the fruit as soon as the borrower declares I'm ready
to pay up, that, you know, he cannot keep on benefiting from
the land. However, איזהו אדרה וסיימי זוזי, Eizehu adara ve'saimei zuzei, if
he says wait, wait, let me go and I have to make
a few phone calls and I'll put in a few offers and
then I'll collect the money. I'm not just going to the ATM
machine but I'm ready to pay up, just give me a little
time. So what's the story? Is that enough to now say that
the lender who's on the land can no longer be reaping the
benefits because it's like he's already triggered the fact that now he's
going to be getting him kicked off? So רבינא אמר אכיל, Ravina
amar achil, you can continue eating. ומר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי אמר
לא אכיל, U'Mar Zutra brei de'Rav Mari amar lo achil, he can't
continue eating. והלכתא לא אכיל, Ve'hilcheta lo achil, the halacha is he
can't continue eating. Of course, you know, if somebody is always saying
wait, wait, wait, just give me a little more time, I'm going
to go get the
money, so presumably you have to have some context in which it
is not just hopeful that he's going to get the money, that
there's actually something concrete, it's not exactly clear what the parameters are
or everybody would just say that. All right.
Now,
רב כהנה ורב פפא ורב אשי לא אכלי בנכייתא. Rav Kahana ve'Rav
Papa ve'Rav Ashi lo achli be'nechyata. Rav Kahana, Rav Papa, and Rav
Ashi did not eat with even this נכייתא. nechyata. Earlier at the
top of the עמוד amud
we said that you know, a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham should not
eat,
you know, except with—sorry, nobody is allowed to benefit without
נכייתא, nechyata, without deducting something from the principal even a small amount,
but a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham shouldn't even agree to that type
of a transaction even with נכייתא, nechyata, it's too close to ריבית
ribbit and you would need the case of משכנתא דסורא. mashkanta de'Sura.
So now it's telling us that רב כהנה ורב פפא ורב אשי
Rav Kahana ve'Rav Papa ve'Rav Ashi all were consistent with that statement
earlier of רבא Rava in the name of רב יוסף Rav Yosef
and they wouldn't do this exchange, they would not lend money and
eat the produce with נכייתא nechyata even with a small deduction. Presumably
if they were ever going to do something it would be משכנתא
דסורא mashkanta de'Sura or this other thing in the גמרא Gemara called
קיצוצה. kitzutsa. רבינא אכיל בנכייתא. Ravina achil be'nechyata.
But רבינא Ravina agreed to eat with נכייתא nechyata and he was
not concerned with the earlier discussion. Now there's a whole major, you
know, about the statement of רבא. Rava. Now there's a whole major
debate in the ראשונים Rishonim because different statements of רבינא Ravina seem
to be contradicting whether you are allowed to eat with נכייתא nechyata
or not. There's a statement way at the beginning of the פרק.
perek. Anyway, it's a major debate. Some say that even רבינא Ravina
would only allow it with a case of אתרא דלא מסלקי Astra
de-lo Mesalki where you cannot remove the person, where it's more like
he has real rights and it's a real purchase, otherwise it's closer
to
ריבית. Ribbis. And some explain even if רבינא Ravina would allow that,
למעשה l'maaseh we don't allow any situation of נחיתא Nachyeisa even with
אתרא דלא מסלקי Astra de-lo Mesalki unless you do משכנתא דסורא, Mashkanta
de-Sura, others would be more permissive with a case of אתרא דלא
מסלקי. Astra de-lo Mesalki. So there's a whole major debate in the
ראשונים Rishonim which way we
פוסקין. pasken. Okay. אמר מר זוטרא: Amar Mar Zutra: מאי טעמא דמאן
דאכל בנחיתא? Mai taama de-man d'achil benachyeisa? What's the reason of רבינא
Ravina of somebody who agrees to eat with the deduction? And we'll
see that this will be a case which will even be similar
to case of
אתרא דמסלקי. Astra de-Mesalki. That says that we don't have to consider
that ריבית, Ribbis, you are deducting a small amount each year even
though the benefit you get certainly significantly exceeds it. It's not ריבית
Ribbis because of the way רש"י Rashi put it, you never really
know that you're going to reap benefit, it's always a certain degree
of a risk, it's a field, it's not like a house where
it's a definite fixed amount that you
benefit. And you're reducing the debt by a small amount, so it's
like a purchase. So that's the
idea why those that permit it permit it. But what's a basis
to see, where's a model that we can see that? So מידי
דהוה אשדה אחוזה, mi-di de-havei a-sadeh achuza, like the case of somebody
that sanctifies to הקדש hekdesh his inherited field. שדה אחוזה, Sadeh achuza,
לאו אף גב דקא אכיל פירי טובא, lav afgav de-cha-achil peiri tuva,
in the case of a שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, even though you
eat a lot of fruit, אמר רחמנא קפרק ליה בארבע זוזי, amar
rachmana kaparklei b'arba zuzei, that you redeem it with just four זוז
zuz a סלע. sela. What does this mean? It means that the
תורה Torah basically says that if you sanctify a
שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, then you have the right to redeem it,
you have to figure out how many years it's going to be
till the יובל, yovel, and if you sanctified it right at the
beginning of the יובל, yovel, then it would be 50
סלע, sela, and then for every year that הקדש hekdesh has a
chance to plant it and harvest it that you haven't redeemed it,
so now you would redeem it for one שקל shekel and change
less. So if it was let's say halfway in, you would redeem
it for 25 שקל. shekel. If it was one year in, you
would redeem it for 49 שקל, shekel, I mean it's 48 and
change, but because you have to divide by 49 or whatever, you
don't divide by 50, but anyway. Okay, or 48. Anyway, so that's
the basic point. So the גמרא Gemara says, well let's look at
this. You have the right, it's like, I mean you didn't borrow
money, but conceptually, you have to give הקדש hekdesh 50 שקל, shekel,
right?
And you can do it at any time. So you're like the
borrower of 50 שקל, shekel, you have the right to do it
at any time, it's אתרא דמסלקי. Astra de-Mesalki.
הקדש hekdesh gets the benefit, could be thousands of dollars worth of
benefit each year from the field.
And what happens to you at the end of the year? They
got thousands of dollars of benefit, your debt, your ability to redeem
it now is reduced by one סלע, sela, by one שקל. shekel.
So it's a very parallel type of a thing. They get a
lot of benefit and all it does is reduce your debt by
one שקל shekel or the amount it would cost to redeem it.
And but you have the right to redeem it at any time.
So that's like a nice model of אתרא דמסלקי Astra de-Mesalki and
with נחיתא. Nachyeisa. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says top of
ס"ח ע"א, samech chet amud aleph, הכא נמי לא שנא, hacha nami
lo shena, here too would it matter. So that's the model.
ומאן דאסר, U-man d'asar, and one who says no it's forbidden. So
what would he say about the case by הקדש? hekdesh? אמר לך,
Amar lach, שדה אחוזה הקדש היא, sadeh achuza hekdesh hi, ורחמנא אוקמה
אפידיון. ve-rachmana ukma pidyon. You can't compare it, you don't owe money
to הקדש. hekdesh. You sanctified something, and the תורה Torah said if
you want to redeem it, you can redeem it for 50 שקל.
shekel. The תורה Torah went easy on you, just give 50 שקל
shekel doesn't matter what the worth of the field is. So that's
the way it works, and if you redeem it a few years
in, you redeem it for less than 50 שקל, shekel, but it
has nothing to do with a debt, there's not even a concept
of ריבית. Ribbis. Right? Okay, it's a little bizarre, you reduce one
שקל, shekel, they get thousands of dollars, but there's no concern that
they're getting benefit from money that they lent. הכא הלוואה היא, Hacha
halva'ah hi, ומחזי כריבית. u-michzei k'ribbis.
In our case money was lent, and therefore, even though if I
didn't lend you money, I could agree to give you a dollar
each year and benefit from your field, but after I have lent
you a thousand dollars, if we reduce if I pay you now
a dollar and get all this benefit from your field, that seems
like ריבית. ribbis. That seems like an enormous benefit that I am
getting in the wake of having lent you money. All right. אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, אמרו לי סבי דמתא מחסיא, amri li
savei d'masa machasya, the elders of the place מתא מחסיא Masa Machasya
said to me, סתם משכנתא שתא, stam mashkanta shata, a
standard mortgage, a משכון mashkon of
a field. It depends on when the borrower is going to pay
the money. למאי נפקא מינה, le-mai nafka mina, what's the relevant, דאחורי
שתא מצי מסלק ליה ולא לא מצי מסלק ליה de-achorei shata matzi
mesalek lei velo lo matzi mesalek lei that after the lender has
got a year of benefit, only then can the borrower redeem, but
less than that not. Okay, so even in a place of מסלק,
mesalek, the lender has the right for the first year to not
be removed, which makes sense. He's going to plant and invest and
harvest, you know, it's why the Torah also says that, you know,
if you sell a field you can't redeem it for the first
two years because you have to give the person who's taking it
the right to, you know, reap the benefits of what they've invested.
All right. Okay, now, okay. ואמר רב אשי אמרו לי סבי דמתא
מחסיא, Va-amar Rav Ashi amru li savei de-Masa Mechasya, Rav Ashi also
said, the elders of מתא מחסיא Masa Mechasya said to me, מאי
משכנתא, mai mashkanta, what's the meaning of the word משכנתא, mashkanta, like
a משכון, mashkon, but it's the word, you know, collateral, but it's
the word that's used specifically like for a field and in modern
Hebrew, you know, for real estate, for modern Hebrew it's used for
mortgage. דשכונה גבי, de-shchuna gabei, that he is the, it's dwelling by
him or he is the שכן, shachen, he's the neighbor to that
field, the lender. What does that mean? למאי נפקא מינה, le-mai nafka
mina, what's for what הלכה? halacha? לדינא דבר מצרא, le-dina de-bar metzra,
for the הלכה halacha of the person on your border. There's a
הלכה halacha that when I am selling a field, I have to
give first right of refusal to the person who has the bordering
field, right? Because my field is worth, you know, much more to
him because now he can expand his property, you know, if I'm
selling my house and the guy has a yard right next to
mine and he now wants to build a much bigger house or
whatever, that property could be worth a lot more to him than
it could be worth to anybody else. So the הלכה halacha is
that if somebody else has offered me
$150,000 for, you know, for my field, you know, half a million
dollars for my house, I have to first go to my next-door
neighbor and say are you willing to meet that price? And if
he's willing to meet that price, I have to sell it to
him. Okay, that's דינא דבר מצרא dina de-bar metzra because I'm not
losing either way and therefore I should do this, I need to,
you know, it's זה נהנה וזה לא חסר zeh neheneh ve-zeh lo
chaser and I need to do this for my next, you know,
as a, as a, as just, you know, being מענטש mentsh towards
my next-door neighbor. So similarly says the גמרא, Gemara, this person, this
lender, he's like the neighbor and since he's got rights to this
field and he's benefiting from it and all of that, if I
choose to sell it, I have to give him first right of
refusal. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now, wrapping all of this up,
says Rava,
לית הלכתא לא כתרשי פופנאי ולא כשטרי מחוזנאי ולא כחכירי נרשאי. leit
hilcheta lo ke-tarshei Pupnai velo ke-shtarei Mechuznai velo ke-chakirei Narshai. So that's
a funny like rhyming thing. The הלכה halacha is not like the
תרשא tarsha if you remember that's like the money paid to hold
back, you know, like I'll sell it to you now for the
price later if you let me wait for the money we had
that before of פופנאי Pupnai and the, and the documents of מחוזנאי
Mechuznai and the sharecroppers of נרשאי. Narshai. Let's see what this means.
כתרשי פופנאי, Ke-tarshei Pupnai, כתרשי דרב פפא. ke-tarshei de-Rav Pappa. The תרשא
tarsha of Rav Pappa if you remember the case was Rav Pappa
was a, like a mead seller, a beer seller, and people wanted
to buy the beer from him and he was going to wait
a few months until it was a higher value, and they said,
well, we'll pay you that higher value, you know, we'll pay you
that higher value, but we'll pay it to you in a few
months, now we want the beer now. So Rav Pappa thought okay,
that's not ריבית, ribbis, I can sell it to them because anyway
I was going to wait a few months and get that price
and I'm doing them a favor. And the גמרא Gemara says no,
sorry, that's too much like ריבית ribbis because ultimately they are buying
it now and you're letting and you're allowing them to pay you
later and they're going to pay you more later than they would
pay you now. So that's not acceptable even if from your perspective,
you know, you're not making any money.
So the גמרא Gemara already earlier rejected Rav Pappa. שטרי מחוזנאי, Shtarei
Mechuznai, the documents of מחוזא, Mechuza, דזקפי ליה לריוחא אקרנא וכתבי ליה
בשטרא. de-zakpei lei le-rivcha a-karna ve-chatvei lei bi-shtara. Okay, so what they
do is like this and we're going to see in the next
משנה Mishna the case of a case of מחצית שכר, machatzis sachar,
but basically something works like this is that
somebody lends money to, you
know,
I'm going to let, here, the case of מחצית שכר machatzis sachar
is the following.
You want to go ahead and do a business. You want to
be in the, I don't know, you want to be
import-export. So, and you've got this great thing and you want to,
I don't know, buy widgets and sell them and you're going to
make a profit and so on. And you're coming to me to
be your investor, to be your silent partner.
So what we're going to do is the following. I will give
you a thousand dollars. That thousand dollars, we're going to treat half
of it... as a loan and half of it as a פקדון,
pikadon, as basically it's not, it's my money that you have to
watch over. You are going to invest my 500 dollars and your
500 dollars because half of that was a loan. Okay, and you're
going to invest it in your business and you'll make a profit
and so on. And then in the end let's say you make
100 dollars profit, you give me 50 dollars and you take 50
dollars, okay, and then you pay me back all thousand, the 500
of mine that you were like you know פקדון, pikadon, that was
not a loan, that was just my money that you were investing
and the 500 of yours you'll have to pay me back because
that was a loan. So what happened in the end? I lent
you 1000 dollars, I got 50 dollars out of it because you
invested, you got 50 dollars out of it. Great, we should all
go home and that should be fine, but we're going to see
no that actually that was a problem
because since half of it since
that's what should have happened, I got the 50 dollars because it
was my money that got invested, I got the 50 dollars, that
makes sense, you know, you got your 50 dollars for your money
that was invested. The only problem is that why did you do
me the favor of investing my money? Right? Why were you working
for me to invest my money so that I could reap the
profits? It's because I lent you the money so that you could
also invest it. So that's a ריבית ribbis problem. All right, so
I have to pay you for your efforts for investing and that
was what we'll see in the next משנה mishna so that then
when if I pay you let's say 10 dollars for your service
for investing the money then I can get my 50 and you
can get your 50 and even though I did this favor of
lending you money that allowed you to invest, you paid me for
that favor not by the work you did but excuse me
you did not pay me for that favor because that work that
you did I paid you 10 dollars. That's all going to be
the case in the next משנה. mishna. So what would they do
in the שטר shtar of
מחוזא? Machoza? They would say the following: let's take this case I
just gave. It would say I'm investing 1000 dollars and when you
pay me back you have to pay me back
1050 dollars because we're going to assume that there's going to be
a 10 percent
profit on the investment and that means my 500 will profit 50
dollars. So I am hereby investing 1000 dollars into your business and
you will pay me back
1050 because the 50 dollars we're going to assume is going to
be the profit. Okay, and maybe I pay you 5 dollars for
the work you're doing. Now that's what they would write in the
document. As you can see, this is getting to be close to
a way that you can actually charge ריבית, ribbis, you know, or
charge it's which is the classic היתר עיסקא, heter iska, the way
you can lend money and and get interest without making it a
problem of ריבית. ribbis. We'll discuss that in the משנה. mishna. But
what was the matter with the way they wrote it? They wrote
it the following way. Let's read that.
דזקפי ליה לרווחא אקרנא. dezakefi lei lerevacha akarna. They sort of compute
the profit with the principal. So they say you have to give
me back 1050 dollars. They don't say you have to give
me back 1000, your loan and my פקדון pikadon plus whatever profit
is made from my half. No, it just says you have to
give me back 1050 dollars. Okay. Now and the problem with that
is
מי אמר דהוי רווחא? mi amar dehavi revacha? Who says that it's
going to profit? Maybe it won't profit. Maybe it'll only profit 25
percent and I only get 25 dollars. Maybe it won't profit at
all. Maybe there'll be a loss. So by writing it that way
it's getting very close to ריבית ribbis because I'm giving you a
thousand and you're giving me back 1050. It's not just saying what
we'll figure out what the profit is. So אמר ליה מר בר
אממר לרב אשי amar lei Mar bar Amemar leRav Ashi so מר
בר אממר Mar bar Amemar said to רב אשי: Rav Ashi: אבא
עביד הכי. Abba avid hachi. So you know what? My dad did
that, exactly that. He would lend people he would invest quote-unquote 1000
dollars and say you pay me back
1050. וכי אתו לקמיה מהימן להו. vechi atu lekamei mehemen lehu. But
if they came back to him and they said you know what?
Actually it was a it didn't go so well and we didn't
make a 10 percent profit, we only made a 5 percent profit,
we didn't make any profit, he would believe them. So says oh
you didn't make any profit, fine, just give me back the 1000.
Oh you only made 5 percent? Okay, just give me back my
half of that, just give me back 25. So even though it
was written based on what they expected the profit to be, in
the end it wasn't it was still really linked to the profit.
It wasn't just give me back 5 percent of the money I
gave you. And he would trust them on what that amount would
be. And therefore it wouldn't really be like ריבית. ribbis. Still a
little close because the שטר shtar still says, give me back fifty
dollars more. All right. So anyway, but he says, look, my father
would do that and he would trust them, so it would still
more be like a business investment and not like ריבית. ribis.
So אמר ליה amar lei so רב אשי Rav Ashi said back
to מר Mar the son of אמימר, Ameimar, תנח היכא דאיתא לדידיה,
teneicha de’islei l’didei, that’s all nice and dandy while your father is
still around. אי שכיב ונחית שטרא קמי יתמי, ishachiv v’nachish shtar kamin
yasmei, if your father would have died and now it would be,
you know, the recipients of the money back would be the orphans,
meaning you, מאי הוה, mai havah, what would happen? You
know, you know, he agreed to believe them, but but the, you
know, you didn't agree to believe them, and the שטר shtar says
that they are flat obligated this money, so it’s a ריבית ribis
problem.
הוה כשגגה שיוצא מלפני השליט, hava k'shigaga she'yotzei milifnei hashallit, it was
like an error that went out from the ruler, meaning, you know,
he’s just סתם stam saying and let's say your father died, and
you know the גמרא Gemara often talks like, you know, that the
רבנים rabbis have this power that when they say things it's like
they can come true. So he let that
slip, ונח נפשיה דאמימר, v'nach nafshih d'ameimar, and אמימר Ameimar טאקע taka
did die. All right, but the problem with this is that even
though it's okay to do an investment in somebody's business, when you
don't write it that it's based on the profit and you fix
the amount and you put it in the שטר, shtar, that makes
it a lot like ריבית. ribis. We'll discuss very soon how this
is going to play out with terms of a היתר עיסקא. heter
iska. Okay, חכירי דנרשאי, chakirei d'narshai, what are the case of the
sharecroppers of
נרשאי? Narshai? דכתבי הכי, de-kasvi hachi, they would write the
following: משכן ליה פלניא ארעא לפלניא mashkein lei planya ara l'planya והדר,
v'hadar,
excuse me,
פלניא planya הכי משכן ליה פלניא ארעא לפלניא, hachi mashkein lei planya
ara l'planya, so-and-so put up his field collateral to like ראובן Reuven
put up his field collateral to שמעון, Shimon, so שמעון Shimon lent
money and now he's, you know, holding onto ראובן's Reuven field like
the cases we saw before, והדר חכרה מיניה, v’hadar chachra minei, and
then ראובן Reuven came back and, you know, rented it from שמעון.
Shimon. All right,
so
here we go. ראובן Reuven borrows money from שמעון. Shimon. As we
learned before, שמעון Shimon can go ahead now, let's say it's a
case of נכייתא, nachyata, let's say we say נכייתא nachyata is okay,
שמעון Shimon can go ahead and deduct a hundred dollars a year
from the loan and benefit from the field. And as רש״י Rashi
explains, that's we're able to say it's not blatant ריבית ribis because
you don't know whether that investment will actually profit or not. All
right, so it's a risk, so he's able to do that even
though he's only deducting a hundred dollars from the loan. But now
שמעון Shimon instead of planting the field, goes ahead and rents it
back to ראובן Reuven for five hundred dollars a year. So the
effect is that ראובן Reuven borrowed whatever money he borrowed, ten thousand
dollars, and is giving שמעון Shimon four hundred dollars a year. Not
that שמעון Shimon is getting the benefit of the field, but שמעון
Shimon is renting the field, you know, sharecropping the field back to
ראובן Reuven and getting a flat four hundred dollars a year. Sounds
like a brilliant way to get ריבית, ribis, but that's the problem,
it's a bit of הערמת ריבית. haramas ribis. So let's take a
look. So that that doesn't work.
אימת קנה דאקניה ניהליה, eimas kanah d'aknyah nihalei, when did שמעון Shimon
ever take possession of the field that he could go ahead and
rent it back to ראובן? Reuven? All right, now if it's like,
maybe it's אתרא דמסלקי דלא מסלקי asra d'mesalkei d'lo mesalkei where it
is like he took possession of the field, but anyway at the
end of the day this is way too much like ריבית ribis
because then שמעון Shimon winds up getting a flat fee each year.
והאידנא, v’idna, then says the גמרא, Gemara, but nowadays דקא כתבי הכי,
d’kach katvi hachi, that people actually do exactly this. קנינא מיניה ושהינא
קמיה עידני והדר חכרה, kanina minei v'shahina kamei idnei v'hadar chachra, כדי
שלא תנעל דלת בפני לווין. kedei shelo tin'al delet bifnei lovin. So
what we do is that like in order to make it work,
because this is the
practice, so שמעון Shimon does a קנין kinyan from ראובן Reuven to
demonstrate that he really is taking possession of the field. And then
he goes ahead and first two years or whatever he actually does
plow it and he harvests it. So שמעון Shimon does things to
demonstrate that he is the owner, you know, he has rights to
this field. After that, then he's allowed to go ahead and rent
it back to ראובן Reuven and get a fixed amount every year.
So the גמרא Gemara says so that would be a way we
do it because in order not to lock the door before lenders,
people got to borrow money, so this is a way that they're
and people don't want to lend money if they're not getting interest,
so this is a way we make it work. But the גמרא
Gemara says ולאו מילתא היא, v'lav milsa hi, but that's not really
the case, the case is it really does remain a problem. Now
there's a lot of factors that mentioned here, is it an אתרא
דמסלקי asra d’mesalkei or an אתרא דלא מסלקי? asra d’lo mesalkei? You
know, is it נחייתא, nach'yasa, is it not נחייתא, nach'yasa, if you
wind up and do do it, what degree of a problem it
is, רש"י Rashi says if you do it it's actually ריבית קצוצה,
ribbis ketzutza, whereas a lot of other ראשונים Rishonim say that it's
only אבק ריבית, avak ribbis, but anyway, that is the case and
so what we see here is two ways in which people try
to get around the ריבית, ribbis, one is by investing money but
having a fixed amount set as the profit, and the גמרא Gemara
says no, you don't know it's going to be that fixed amount,
and the other is by having a field as collateral and then
renting it back and also the גמרא Gemara was not happy with
it. But in the end, it's the first of those really is
the one that winds up being the basis for היתר עסקא, hetter
iska, which is something that developed in I think the 17th or
18th century in particular, actually it started much earlier, תרומת הדשן, Terumas
HaDeshen, anyway, and we will discuss it in the context of this
next משנה. Mishnah. So let's look at the משנה. Mishnah.
אין מושיבין חנווני למחצית שכר, ein moshivin chanvani lemachatzis sachar, okay, you
cannot have a storekeeper sit to get half of the profit. So
this is what I was explaining before. I go ahead and I
say to somebody, okay, here is, you know, my 20 barrels of
wine,
I'm going to go ahead
and you will sell them for
me, and I will get half the profit and you'll keep half
the profit. Now, if we just did it like that, it's great!
You're doing the work, you're selling it, and what am I paying
you? I'm paying you half the profit. But, when normally we do
this type of a thing, like a silent partner and the active
partner and so on, the assumption is, the גמרא Gemara sort of
works with the assumption, that the arrangement is that half is a
loan and half is I retain ownership and half I've lent to
you. Now, why would I do this? Because, if it's all my
wine and I'm paying you with half of the profit, then it's
all great if we make a profit, but let's say, you know,
the wine spills and it's a loss, I'm now going to have
to suffer all the loss. Okay? Let's say the wine goes down
in value, I'm the one that gets the hit. So, if what
we really want to do is not me just hire you to
sell my wine, what we really want to do is go into
partnership where we each take half the liability and get half of
the benefit. So then the way that that works, it would work
great if it was half my money and half your money. But
it's not that way, it's all my money. So, when I give
you the 100 barrels of wine, what we'll say is I'm lending
you 50 barrels, and now you have 50 barrels, I have 50
barrels, we both have half the money, we put it in, we're
equal partners and you're going to go ahead and do the work
and we're going to split the profit. So it's a partnership, silent
partnership, and I'm the silent partner, you're the one who does the
active work, we split the profit. So that's called מחצית שכר. machatzis
sachar. You get a half of the profit because that's the half
that's your 50 barrels of wine, right, that I lent you but
now they're yours. So that's your half of the business and I
get the other profit from the other 50 barrels, that's my half
of the business. And the benefit to me is that now I
am distributing my
risk. If the wine spills, if it goes down in value, we're
both taking, we're sharing in the profits and we're sharing in the
losses. It's a real partnership. So if I start with all the
money, the way you create a real partnership is effectively I lend
you half and then we both go in equally. The only problem
with that is, and this is what I was saying before, is
that you're now working for me for free. Why are you doing
all the work? Because I gave you the 50 barrels of wine,
because I lent you the money. So, if you had equally put
in your own money, then we would split the work. So I
can't do that, I can't benefit from your work for having lent
you the money. That's ריבית. ribbis. So therefore, I have to pay
you for your efforts in investing and then we'll split the profit.
Okay, so let's read that again. אין מושיבין חנווני למחצית שכר, ein
moshivin chanvani lemachatzis sachar, you cannot have a
storekeeper, I cannot sit him down to get half of the profits
and, again, we're equally liable for losses, equally share in profits, without
paying him. Okay. ולא יתן מעות ליקח בהן פירות למחצית שכר, velo
yitein ma'os likach bahen peiros lemachatzis sachar, also let's say a case
of like
import-export merchandise, I can't just give him money and say go ahead,
you know, buy apples in this orchard, come to the market, sell
it, you'll make a profit and so on, and I'm investing the
money, we can't do that and we split the profits if we're
also splitting the losses, if it's a real partnership, we can't do
that אלא אם כן נותן לו שכר כתפו, ella im kein nosein
lo sechar ketafo, unless I pay him like a worker. Alright, so
again. If it was all my loss, then I can of course.
He gets half of the profits or he gets 10% of the
profits, that's my fee to him. But if we want it to
be a partnership, the only way it becomes a partnership and we
equally share the losses and equally share the gains is if I
lent him half the money. And then he can't work for me
for free, I have to pay him.
Okay. אין מושיבין תרנגולים למחצית. Ein moshivin tarnegolim lemachatzit. Similarly, if I
have eggs, I can't go ahead and say to you and you
have chickens or and hens, I can't say have your hen sit
on my eggs and hatch them into chicks. I don't know how
I got eggs without them having hens, anyway. But I can't go
ahead and do that and you do the work and then we
split the profit. Again and also we equally share in the risk.
Can't do that unless I'm going to pay you.
ואין שמין עגלים וסיחים למחצה. Ve'ein shamin agalim vesiyachim lemachtza. And also
I can't have you go ahead and raise my calves and my
foals for, and you're going to do the work of raising them,
you don't have any calves and foals of your own, and then
we're going to, you know, sell them and split the profits, the
difference between how much they sold for and how much they were
worth. So again, we can't do that if we're going to share
in the risk and share in the gains unless I pay you.
אלא אם כן נותן לו שכר עמלו ומזונו, Ela im kein notein
lo sechar amalo umezono, unless I pay you for your effort and
also expenses. Here there are expenses because you got to feed the
animals. אבל מקבלין עגלים וסיחים למחצה ומגדלין אותן עד שיהיו משולשים וחמור
עד שתהא טוענת. Aval mekabelin agalim vesiyachim lemachtza umegadlin otan ad sheyihyu
meshulashim vechamor ad shetehei toenet. But if you don't say assess their
value, you don't say, "Okay, these foals are now worth a thousand
dollars," okay, and why are you assessing their value? Because your plan
is they're worth a thousand dollars, in the end you'll sell them,
they'll be worth ten thousand dollars, you'll figure out the difference, nine
thousand dollars, you'll, you know, split the profit. So you would assess
their values if you were doing this idea of a partnership. But
if I'm not assessing the values, I'm just saying, "Here are my
calves, go ahead and raise them," it doesn't matter what they're worth,
you're going to sell them and I'll get the profit. So in
that type of a case, right, it's you're just working for me.
It's not a partnership. If it was a partnership, you'd have to
know how much they were worth. So I can give you my
things to raise
למחצה lemachtza and, hold on a minute, ומגדלין אותן
עד שיהיו משולשים
umegadlin otan
ad sheyihyu meshulashim and
you raise them until they're like a third grown, whatever that means,
וחמור עד שתהא טוענת vechamor ad shetehei toenet and if it's a
donkey until it's able to handle a load. Now how much you're
profiting, it does say you are profiting half, 50%. So it's a
little funny because in order to know how much the profit was,
you would have to assess what their value is right now. So
it's not exactly clear to me how that works. But anyway, Rashi
says that by not assessing the value what you're clearly not, it's
clear that you who's doing the work do not have to assume
half the risk. If you were going to have to assume half
the risk, we would have to know how much is the value
of what you are receiving right now. Okay. So that is the
principle and this is the idea of מחצית שכר. machatzit sechar. תנא,
Tana, says the Gemara, we taught in the Baraita, כפועל בטל, Kepoeil
batel, that you pay him like a פועל בטל poeil batel who
is not working. מאי כפועל בטל? Mai kepoeil batel? What does a
non-working worker mean? אמר אביי כפועל בטל של אותה מלאכה דבטל מינה.
Amar Abaye kepoeil batel shel ota melacha debatel mineih. Like a worker
who is not working from that work that he is not working
in. Okay, so what does any of that mean? So Rashi says
that this is to some, that this means that if let's say
working in the store, you know, would normally pay ten dollars an
hour, and you have work in chopping logs that pays you twenty
dollars an hour. So, you know, how much would you pay, would
you accept to do the work of selling in a store? You
know, you wouldn't probably demand twenty dollars because it would be a
heck of a lot easier. But ten dollars wouldn't be enough because
you're, you know, you need to earn money to put food on
the table. So you might agree to take eighteen dollars for that.
So that's פועל בטל דבטל מהאי מלאכה דבטל מינה. poeil batel debatel
mehai melacha debatel mineih. The work I'm asking you to leave, you're
chopping logs, how much would you accept to do this easier work
of working in the store? Now that is the really, in other
places that makes sense; in this context, it makes very little sense.
Because why should I pay you? We have to just get around
the ribis problem. And presumably you want to go in this business,
you want to go ahead and buy and sell the fruit or,
you know, invest the money or whatever you want to do. Why
should I pay you for leaving your job of chopping logs, right?
Why don't I just pay you whatever the normal fee is for
somebody to do that type of work? So it's a very hard
read and later in the Gemara, the Gemara is going to talk
like the math that the Gemara does also doesn't make sense according
to that read. The better understanding is, you know, what... the way
רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* and a version of it רמב"ן *Ramban* are
saying, which is no, you pay him for somebody who's just sitting
around and doing nothing. Somebody sitting around and doing nothing, how much
would you be willing to take to work in a store? You
know, that's always the way it is in a job market, right?
If somebody already has a job, you know, you gotta pay him
more, like it's more competition. But if somebody's out of work and
has no work, you can pay them less. So that's the way
רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says, the רמב"ן *Ramban* has a slight, has
a somewhat of a variation on it. Okay, that's what you pay.
וצריכא *U-tzricha*,
and you need to tell me both the case of working in
the store and the case of buying and of like investing the
money. דאי תנא חנוני *De-i tanah chanvani*, if it had just said
the storekeeper, חנוני דסגי ליה כפועל בטל *chanvani de-sagi lei ke-poel batel*,
by the חנוני *chanvani* it's enough to pay him like this פועל
בטל *poel batel*, משום דלא נפיש טרחא *mishum de-lo nafish tarcha* because
it's not a lot of effort to sit in a store and
to sit behind the cash register. אבל מעות ליקח בהן פירות *Aval
mo'is likach bahen peirot*, but money to go and to go to
the, you know, to go to the fields and to buy and
to bring them back to the city and to sell it, דנפיש
טרחא *de-nafish tarcha* that it's a lot of effort, אימא לא סגי
ליה כפועל בטל *eima lo sagi lei ke-poel batel* it might not
be enough to pay him like a פועל בטל *poel batel*. Here's
by the way why it's again hard for רש"י *Rashi* because for
רש"י *Rashi* you're always factoring in how hard is this other work
that you would have done and the work that you're doing now.
Really shouldn't make a difference, but anyway, but that seems to be
that פועל בטל *poel batel* is a much more minor cost and
we're saying that little amount of פועל בטל *poel batel*, that might
not be enough if the work you're doing is really heavy work.
ואי תנא מעות ליקח בהן פירות *Ve-i tanah mo'is likach bahen peirot*
and had it taught the case about money, you know, that that
was the case I have to pay you like a פועל בטל
*poel batel*, הוה אמינא התם הוא דבעי כפועל בטל *hava amina hatam
hu de-ba'ei ke-poel batel* it's okay when you're doing this hard work
of investing the money and bringing the fruit, buying it out in
the field and bringing it back, then I have to pay you
a פועל בטל *poel batel*, משום דנפיש טרחא *mishum de-lo nafish tarcha*
because there's a lot of effort, אבל חנוני דלא נפיש טרחא *aval
chanvani de-lo nafish tarcha* but if all you're doing is selling the
store and sitting behind the counter, אימא סגי ליה במשהו בעלמא *eima
sagi lei be-mashehu be-alma* maybe even a trivial amount would be okay.
What's a trivial amount? אפילו טבלי עמו בציער *Afilu tavlei imo be-tzi'ir*,
let's say all we did is I asked, you know, you were,
I offered you some of my brine or whatever, you know, to
dip your bread in. You know, I gave you a little piece
of bread or I gave you a dip or something. ולא אכל
עמו אלא גרוגרת אחת *Ve-lo achal imo ela gergores achat* or I
gave you like a, you know,
a pressed fig or something.
זהו שכרו *Zehu secharo*, I might have thought that suffices. You know,
if it's so easy sitting in a store, maybe something completely trivial
we would have been enough to get around the רבית *ribbit* problem
to say, Oh well I'm paying him, I gave him a piece
of gum. Now we're going to see that there's going to be
a תנא *Tanna* who says this, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s not making
that up out of anywhere. וצריכא *Tzricha*, so therefore it had to
say both cases, whether it's heavy work or light work. In order
to get out of the רבית *ribbit* problem and we're going to
split the profit and split the loss, then in order to get
out of it, I have to pay you like a פועל בטל
*poel batel*, whatever that amount is, which is debated as I said
between רש"י *Rashi*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* and other ראשונים *Rishonim*. So now
we're going to see a ברייתא *Baraita* that has a couple of
opinions about how much you have to pay, and it's not exactly
clear which one is the פועל בטל *poel batel* opinion. Let's take
a look. Okay, we'll skip the parenthesis. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan, *Tanu
rabanan*, our Rabbis taught, כמה הוא שכרו *kamahu secharo*,
what's his fee if you need to pay this guy for this
deal of this partnership. בין מרובה בין מועט דברי רבי מאיר *Bein
meruba bein mu'at, divrei Rabi Meir*, whether a little or a lot,
that's what רבי מאיר *Rabi Meir* says. So
what
does that mean? So רש"י *Rashi* says it means whatever you agree
upon. Okay, you just have to agree on a certain amount. Others
say that this is the פועל בטל *poel batel* position and it
means, you know, based on whether the work is a lot of
work or not a lot of work, but it's the פועל בטל
*poel batel* position. But רש"י *Rashi* says it means whatever you agree
upon. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, אומר אפילו לא טבל עמו אלא בציער
ולא אכל עמו אלא גרוגרת אחת זהו שכרו *Rabi Yehuda omer afilu
lo taval imo ela be-tzi'ir ve-lo achal imo ela gergores achat zehu
secharo*, like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* alluded to before. No, any trivial
benefit, that counts as his fee. We're getting out of a רבית
*ribbit* problem, it looks like, you know, we don't want it to
be רבית *ribbit*, so we can sort of do it with a
wink and a nod and you just give him a dollar, you
give him a piece of gum, that's your fee and for that
you are spending all this effort, you know, doing all this work.
זהו שכרו *Zehu secharo*. רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר נותן לו שכרו
מושלם *Rabi Shimon ben Yochai omer notin lo secharo mushlam*, or you
have to give him the full, his full fee. So רש"י *Rashi*
says that means that's the פועל בטל *poel batel* position.
Others say it means something else. Okay. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*, our
Rabbis taught, אין שמין לא את העזים ולא את הרחלים *ein shamin
lo et ha-izim ve-lo et ha-rechelim*, you do not assess the value
for, you know, for goats and for lambs, ולא כל דבר שאינו
עושה ואוכל למחצה *ve-lo kol davar she-eino oseh ve-ochel le-mechtzah* and not,
or nothing that does not produce anything you do not do this
half and half, meaning without paying the person. If it were something
that would produce something, let's say it was a cow that produces
milk, then I can say, you know, you raise the cow and
we split the profit, you know, you're going to make it bigger
and bigger and put meat and we're going to שחט *shecht* it
eventually and we'll split the profit and split
the
loss. the goat and the sheep and so on until it gets
bigger and it's not producing anything, then we can't do the 50/50
loss and profit if it's all my sheep and I'm giving it
to you, unless I pay you something. Okay, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda אומר שמין את העיזין מפני שחולבות ואת
הרחלים מפני שגוזזות ושוטפות ומורטות. He says no, you can do it
because the goats actually give off milk, so that can be your
fee. And the lambs, first of all you can shear them and
if they walk through water, some of their wool will fall off
in the
water and if they walk through thorns that'll pull off some of
their wool, so all of that will count as your fee.
והתרנגולת מפני שעושה ואוכלת. Ve-ha-tarnegolet mipne she-osa ve-ochelet. But everybody presumably agrees
that the case of the chicken you can do because you raise
chickens and I give you the chickens, they're all my chickens, you
raise them, we split, they get
bigger, we take equal share of the loss and the profits and
you get the eggs. So everybody agrees we can do with the
eggs. Okay. ותנא
קמא גיזה וחלב לא ספק לשכר עמלו ומזונו. Ve-Tana Kama giza ve-chalav
lo sapek li-schar amalo u-mezonot. So the גמרא Gemara says I don't
get it. So that idea that you can milk the goats and
you get the shearings of the sheep, that's an excellent point. Why
does the first opinion not think that that would count as your
fee?
So the גמרא gemara says בגיזה וחלב כולי עלמא לא פליגי. Be-giza
ve-chalav kulei alma lo pligi. Everybody agrees when it comes to the
actual real shearing and real milk, everybody agrees that yes of course
if you want to give the worker that, that will count. כי
פליגי בנסיובי וטוטורי. Ki pligi be-nisyovei ve-totrei. What they're really arguing about
is not the actual milk but like the water left of the
milk after you remove it, after you remove all the curds and
whey or whatever, and טוטורי totrei which is
the fuzzy stuff that comes off of the sheep not when you
actually shear them but the other thing that gets caught in the
thorns and the thistles. So that's what they're debating. If you really
let the person keep the milk and really let them keep the
shearing, of course it would be okay. But the question is no,
you're only letting them get like this dross. Okay, that's what you're
giving your worker. So, תנא קמא סבר לה
כרבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Tana Kama savar lah ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai.
The first position holds like רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai who said that you have to give him דהפסידו ממה שנתן
לו שכר מושלם, de-hefseidu mi-ma she-natan lo sachar mushlam, that you have
to give him the full fee and obviously this dross does not
count as his full fee for his work. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
סבר לה כאבוה Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda savar lah ke-avuha and
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה holds like his father, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda
דאמר אפילו לא טבל עמו אלא בציר ולא אכל עמו אלא גרוגרת
אחת זהו שכרו. de-amar afilu lo taval imo ela be-tzir ve-lo achal
imo ela grogeret achat zehu sacharo. Okay, that even if
you only dipped your bread
in the oil or whatever it
was or you gave him a pressed fig, that's enough. So also
some geezings and shearings, that would be enough. תוספות says that it
would not be enough for the what do you call it for
the actual cost of the fee, but assuming you paid for the
actual expenses it would be enough for רבי יהודה for the fee
for the effort. Okay, so we will end here and I should
just say that this is this whole idea of investing in a
business becomes the basis for the היתר עסקא. Heter Iska. And here's
basically I'll just end with saying here's how a היתר עסקא Heter
Iska basically works. Okay, it's the same idea. I'm going to lend
you 10,000 dollars for your business. Now let's say you don't have
a business. So I'm going to say, and you really need it
to put food on the table, so I'm going to say well
no I'm going to give you 10,000 dollars for anything that you're
doing. Even if you're not going to use this 10,000 dollars to
go ahead let's say but
whatever business you find, whatever effort you want to put it to,
any good work that you are doing, even if you're not using
this 10,000 dollars directly for it, this 10,000 dollars is getting me
a 10,000 dollar portion in any business that you have, in any
profit-making venture that you have. It becomes a little bit of a
problem if the person has absolutely nothing that's earning income. But anyway,
that's the fiction. Okay? So I give you 10,000 dollars to invest
in your business. Okay and it's half הלוואה halva'ah and half פיקדון
pikadon like we said. What is my fee to you? We're going
to see in the גמרא that one way instead of giving you
a fee is that I could share a big I could take
a bigger portion of the loss of the risk. So two-thirds of
the risk will be mine, one-third will be yours. So that you
are not taking as big a portion in the risk, that effectively
is your fee. Okay great. Now
that's not going to get me just necessarily a good return on
my investment. How are you going to use it? Maybe there'll be
a loss. How are we going to deal with all of those
issues if you're not really going to invest it? So what we're
going to say is the following. We're going to say first of
all that you are not believed
to say
whether there was a loss
or what the profit was. You're not believed to make any of
those
claims unless you have to do something very, very difficult. You have
to make a שבועה shvua with a ספר תורה, sefer torah, you
need עדים, edim, you need whatever, we make some very difficult standard
for you to claim what actually happened. Okay, but I'm going to
go easy on you and I will say to you that actually
I will, if you pay me a fee, if you pay
me—I'm investing $10,000 in your business—if you pay me $1,000 a year,
then I waive my right to know from you what the profit
was, what the loss was, and you can keep all the profits
to yourself. So that's essentially how we do it, that by you
giving me a fee of $1,000, I am entitling you to not
have to prove profit and loss and you get to keep all
the rest of the profits for yourself. And that becomes essentially what
a היתר עסקא heter iska is and how we can lend money
with ריבית ribbis without it actually being ריבית. ribbis. All right, we
will end here for now. You know what, let's actually do one
little more piece before we totally wrap up. Okay, תנו רבנן, משכרת
אשה לחברתה תרנגולת בשני אפרוחים. maskeret isha le-chavertah tarnegolet bi-shnei efrochim. This
is very similar to what we said before. A woman
can
lend out her hen to keep two chicks. She's going to have
the hen sit on eggs and they'll grow into chicks and her
fee will be two chicks. So fine, that's not a 50-50 partnership,
you're just paying her with two chicks and the rest, they're your
eggs and you get to keep
all the others.
אשה שאמרה לחברתה תרנגולת שלי וביצים שליכי. isha she-amra le-chavertah tarnegolet sheli
ve-beitzim shelichi. Now, however, if somebody said to their friend, 'Hey, it's
my hen, your eggs, ואני ואת נחלוק באפרוחים, va-ani ve-at nachlok ba-efrochim,
let's split the chicks.' So as soon as you say the word
split, it's understood to be a partnership and a partnership where you
share in the risk and share in the profit. So now there's
a problem: it's their eggs, you're the one lending
the hen, doing the effort as it were, what's your fee that
you're getting if they're the one investing and risking all the eggs
and now it's becoming a partnership and it's splitting the profits and
splitting the losses? So רבי יהודה מתיר, rabbi yehuda matir, Rabbi Yehuda
says that's okay, you don't have to pay. רבי שמעון אוסר, rabbi
shimon oser, Rabbi Shimon forbids. So the גמרא says רבי יהודה לא
בעי שכר עמלו ומזונו, rabbi yehuda lo ba-ei sechar amalo u-mezono, doesn't
Rabbi Yehuda need the effort and the feed? Again, we know Rabbi
Yehuda has a low standard, but you need at least something. איכא
ביצים מוזרות, ika beitzim muzarot, no, what you have is you have
the eggs that are not fertilized and those eggs actually are you
want to grow them into chicks, so the assumption is that you'll
get to keep that. So again, for Rabbi Yehuda who has a
very low standard, that will suffice. Okay, we'll end with this here,
more to be continued tomorrow.